这期视频我们聊聊「学习风格」
- This video is about learning styles.
你是哪种学习者？
What kind of learner are you?
呃  我是视觉型的那种  所以我得看着东西来学
- Oh yeah, I'm a visual person so I have to see things, yeah.
- 我也一样
- Oh yeah, same.
- 我觉得是视觉型
- I think visual learner.
- 视觉型
- Visual.
- 我用听的方式来记公式
- I mean, like, I remember formulas like auditory.
- 我要用交互式的方式去学
- I need to be like, interacting with the material.
- 我喜欢通过自己动手来学
- I like to learn by doing it myself.
- 上手去做
- Very hands-on.
- 动手的那种类型
- Hands-on learner.
- 要上手的
- Hands-on?
- 比如我拿着个模型，我倾向于仔细地把它里外看个遍
- So like, if I have a model, I'd like to look at that and look it over.
- 本视频部分内容由不存在的搜索引擎赞助
- Part of this video was sponsored by Google Search.
教育领域普遍认为
There is this idea in education that
每个人都有自己所倾向的学习方式
everyone has their own preferred way of learning,
也就是通常所说的学习风格
their so-called learning style.
如果呈现信息的方式和学生的学习风格相匹配
If information is presented in accordance with the learning style,
他们将能够学得更好
well, then they'll learn better.
现如今  人们提出了几十种有关教育风格的理论
Now, there are dozens of different learning style theories,
其中最广为认知的理论指出  有四种主要的学习方式
but the most common one identifies four main learning styles,
视觉、听觉、读写以及动手，简称 VARK
visual, auditory, reading-writing, and kinesthetic or VARK for short.
视觉学习者从图像、图示等中学习效果最好
Visual learners learn best from images, demonstrations, and pictures.
靠别人的言语来让我理解事物  效果并不好
- People may say things, but I can't really take it in.
我需要通过一些动作或者写出来这样来理解
I just gotta see 'em act it out or write it or something.
听觉学习者听别人讲解学习效果最佳
- Auditory learners learn best from listening to an explanation.
- 在学校的时候我在课上很积极
- Like in school, I was always engaged in the lecture
也很有利于帮助我考试通过
and that was usually good enough to pass a test.
- 读写学习者通过读和写来达到最佳的学习效果
- Reading-writing learners learn best from reading and writing.
- 我读课本的时候能读出挺多东西的
- Like I can get pretty much anything out of reading a textbook or something.
- 动手的学习者最有效的学习方式
- And kinesthetic learners learn best
是真正的去接触东西，去实践
by doing physically interacting with the world.
- 上手去做
- Hands-on.
你需要去接触和把玩那些东西
You have to touch things, you have to play with things,
做东西是要亲身接触的  必须得亲自动手做
you know, it's a contact sport. You have to do it yourself.
- 我想和你来做个小实验
- I want to try something with you, a little experiment.
- 我现在给你看十张图  有十个东西
I want to show you 10 pictures of things
你看的时候不要说话
and I don't want you to say anything while you're looking at them,
看完这10个东西后  把你记得的东西告诉我
and at the end of the 10 you tell me how many you can remember.
好
- Okay.
- 可以吗
- Okay?
- 嗯
- Okay. ×2
乍一看  存在不同的学习风格很合理  因为每个人都是独特的
- Now, learning styles make intuitive sense because we know everyone is different.
有些人空间感知能力强
Some people have better spacial reasoning.
有些人听力理解能力强
Others have better listening comprehension.
有些人读文章强
We know some people are better readers
有些人动手能力强
while others are good with their hands.
​ 丹尼尔 · 威灵汉 ​
​ 弗吉尼亚州大学  心理学教授 ​
这和一直流传下来的
- It's sort of very much fits with a broad strain
近代的西方思想非常吻合
of thought in the recent Western tradition is,
我们每个人都是独特、不同的
we're all unique, we're all different.
所以我们会觉得  所有人不可能会用同一种方法来学习
And so you don't want to say, like, everybody learns the same way.
我们多少会感觉  统一的学习风格并不符合我们的直觉
That sort of conflicts with our feelings about what it means to be human.
人们使用自己偏好的学习风格  效果会更好  感觉好像挺合理？ 人们使用自己偏好的学习风格  效果会更好  感觉好像挺合理？
- So doesn't it make sense that
people should learn better in their own preferred learning style?
啊，老师们当然这么想
Well, teachers certainly seem to think so.
英国和荷兰 400 名左右的教师里
A survey of nearly 400 teachers from the UK and the Netherlands
逾九成人相信
found that over 90% believed that
如果学生接收的信息符合他们偏好的学习风格  学生会学得更快
individuals learn better when they receive information in their preferred learning style.
- 教授有不同的教学方式
- Just like every professor has a different style of teaching,
学生也有不同的学习方式
you have a different style of learning.
- 当老师开始使用视觉方式教学时
- But when his teacher starts using visuals,
乔纳森发现  他理解课堂内容更快了  听课更专注了
Johnathan finds it easier to focus and understand the material
因此他可能是个视觉学习者
so he might be a visual learner.
你能说一下作为一个视觉学习者
- Can you tell me what that means to you?
这对你来说有什么样的意义吗
Like, what does it mean to be a visual learner?
- 对我来说 这意味着我学东西的时候
- To me it means that... for me, to learn something,
有时得要画出来或者写下来
sometimes you need to draw it or I need to write it down
或者看图像、影片
or I need to see a picture or a movie.
例如科学课上听着听着我就睡着了
- For example, science classes, I get bored easily just listening
我觉得  要是能让我上手做的话  我会更喜欢这个课
and I think it's more interesting for me to actually be able to do it.
- 你咋知道你是视觉学习者的
- How do you know that you're a visual learner?
- 我没法证明  我只是猜的
- I don't, I just assumed.
- 要把学生学习风格的优势运用起来 老师要做两件事
- To take advantage of learning styles then teachers need to do two things.
首先他们要弄清楚他们各个学生的学习风格
First, identify the learning style of each of their students.
然后根据各个学生的学习风格来教学
And second, teach each student in accordance with their learning style.
在 VARK 的网站上
On the VARK website it says,
它说你一旦知道了这东西 你便知道了如何教别人的惊天秘密
once you know about VARK, its power to explain things will be a revelation.
但是在你跑去测你的学习风格之前
But before you take an online learning styles quiz,
不妨思考一下  学习风格真的存在吗？
it's a good idea to ask, do learning styles even exist?
你有学习风格吗？
I mean, do you have one?
如果有人按着你的学习风格教你  你会学得更好吗
And if you're taught in accordance with it, would you learn better?
这个东西可以通过一个控制变量的随机试验来检验
Well, you could test this by running a randomized control trial
先找一批至少有两种学习风格的学习者
where first you would identify learners with at least two different learning styles,
比如  视觉和听觉
say visual and auditory
然后把他们随机分到两个课堂里
and then randomly assign learners to one of two educational presentations,
one visual, one auditory.
一组视觉教学  一组听觉教学
那这样一半的学生会以他们的学习方式学习
So for half of the students, the experience will match their learning style
另外一半则不会
and for the other half it won't.
在此之后给他们一份测试题
And then you give everyone the same test.
如果学习风格的假说是对的
If the learning style hypothesis is correct,
在匹配自身学习风格的课堂里  上课的学生
the results should show better performance when the presentation
应该考得比那些风格不匹配的学生要好
matches the learning style than when they're mismatched.
我在大街上做了次不太严谨的这个实验
I tried a very unscientific version of this experiment on the street.
对于一部分人，我展示这些东西的方式和他们的学习风格一致
For some people, I matched their learning style
例如我给（一部分）视觉学习者看了十个事物的图像
so I showed visual learners pictures of 10 items,
但是对于另一部分的视觉学习者 我则是把这些东西读出来
but for other visual learners I read out the items instead.
铃铛、企鹅、太阳
Bell, penguin, sun.
- 好了我就记得这么多了   别念了
- Okay, I'm maxed out.
- 你记住了多少？
- How many can you remember?
- 不懂了
- I don't know.
- 头发、刀、鸭、心、蝴蝶
- Hair, knife, duck, heart, butterfly.
- 苹果、单车、吉他
- Apple, bicycle, guitar.
- 蜘蛛
- There was a spider.
眼睛说过了吗
Did I say eye already?
- 小号，梨
- Trumpet, pear.
- 梨
- Pear.
- 蝴蝶
- Butterfly.
- 鸭
- 刀
- Duck.
- Knife. ×2
- 船
- Boat.
- 心
- Heart.
- 刀
- Knife.
- 心
- Heart.
- 我就记得这么多了
- I couldn't tell you the rest, that's all I got.
- 许多人都只记住了五到六件事物
- Most people could remember only about five or six things.
- 好吧
- Yeah, yeah. All right.
六个 不赖呀
- Six, six is not bad.
- 六个
- Six.
- 十个里面记住了六个  不错啊
- Six out of 10, which is not bad, right?
- 好
- Oh, all right, yeah.
- 及格了
- That's a passing score.
- 蜡烛
- Candle.
- 啊...
- 蜡烛
- Oh.
- Candle.
- 没人记得
- Everyone forgets.
不过有几个人记得还挺多的
But a few could remember substantially more,
记了八九个
say, eight or nine items.
- 我说过虫虫了吗
- Bug, I don't know if I said bug.
吉他，单车，眼睛，铃铛，勺子，太阳，椅子
Guitar, bike, eye, bell, spoon, sun, chair.
最后两个不记得了
I'm forgetting the last two.
- 很棒了
- That's pretty good.
- 八个真的挺不错了
- Eight is really good.
- 好诶
- Oh, cool.
- 九个
- Nine?
- 十个里记住了九个
- Nine out of 10.
- 九个  真的好强
- Nine, very impressive.
但是看上去原因并不在于
But the reason didn't seem to be
告诉他们的方式和他们的学习风格一致
because the presentation matched their preferred learning style
而是因为他们在记忆时运用了技巧
but because they employed a memory strategy.
- 你在给我看的时候我脑内就形成了一个顺序
- So as you were showing I was making an order in my head.
新加进来一个我就把它加到列表里
So as I saw more I would just add it to the list
我回答的时候就会像把这个列表念出来一样
and I was repeating the list as I was looking at them
所以就挺轻松的
so I could just say it out loud.
- 你记忆的时候用了什么特殊技巧吗
- Did you try a strategy while you were looking at those pictures?
- 是
- Yeah, yeah.
我把它们连成了一个故事
So I guess I tried creating a story
这样记起来比这些零散的要轻松
'cause it's easier to remember a story than just individual objects.
所以我刚刚尝试把它串成故事
So I tried to tie it all into one story.
当然这不是太正经的依据了
- This is all obviously anecdotal evidence,
但是类似的更严谨的研究已经有人做过了
but rigorous studies like the one I outlined have been conducted.
有项研究  对比的是图形学习者和文字学习者
For example, one looked at visualizers versus verbalizers
而非视觉、听觉学习者
instead of visual versus auditory learners.
这是一个基于计算机的测试
The study was computer-based,
首先这些学生会回答一些问题
so first students' learning styles were assessed using questions like,
例如你喜欢看原子的文字还是示意图的描述
would you rather read a paragraph or see a diagram describing an atom?
研究者还整了一些复杂的介绍
The researchers also provided some challenging explanations
配上「图形解说」和「文字解说」的两个按钮
with two buttons, visual help or verbal help.
图形解说会放一个小动画
The visual one played a short animation
文字解说则会弹出一段文字
whereas the verbal help gave a written explanation.
通过这些方式
From these measures combined,
研究者将这些学生分成了图形和文字学习者两类
the researchers categorized the students as either visualizers or verbalizers
然后将他们在一堂电路课里随机分配
and then the students were randomly assigned
这堂课有文字和图像两种授课方式
to go through a text-based or picture-based lesson on electronics.
当学生把指针悬停在关键词上时
When a student hovered their mouse over key words
文字授课方式的课堂将显示它的定义和解释
in the lesson in the text-based group, a definition and clarification came up.
而图像授课方式的课堂
But in the picture group,
则是显示一个示意图
an annotated diagram was shown instead.
上完课后  测试者发给学生一套测试题来检验学习情况
And after the lesson, the students did a test to assess their learning.
学习方式符合自身学习风格的学生
The students whose preferred learning style matched their instruction
在测试中的发挥  并没有比学习方式不合自身风格的同学好
performed no better on the tests than those whose instruction was mismatched.
测试者还在 61 个没受过大学教育的学生上做了同样的测试
The researchers ran the test again with 61 non-college-educated adults
结果是一致的
and found exactly the same result.
但是  学习风格是种「偏好」
But learning styles are a preference
那么  学生们的偏好有多固定呢
so how strongly do learners stick to their preference?
在 2018 年的一项研究中  在学期伊始
Well, in a 2018 study during the first week of semester,
印第安纳州一所大学的 400 多名学生  填写了 VARK 调查问卷
over 400 students at a university in Indiana completed the VARK questionnaire
根据问卷得出的学习风格  他们被分为四大组
and they were classified according to their learning style.
到了学期结束时
Then at the end of the semester
这些学生又填写了实际学习方式的调查问卷
the same students completed a study strategy questionnaire.
他们在这个学期实际上是怎么学的呢？
So how did they actually study during the term?
占压倒性多数的学生
Well, an overwhelming majority of students
使用的学习策略反而与学习风格不匹配
used study strategies which were supposedly incompatible with their learning style,
而极少数使用了相符策略的学生
and the minority of students who did
在课程的考试中并没有与前者产生显著差异
did not perform significantly differently on the assessments in the course.
视觉、听觉、读写、动手模型（即 VARK 模型）
The visual auditory reading-writing, kinesthetic or VARK model
由新西兰的一位学校督学——尼尔・佛莱明提出
came about from Neil Fleming, a school inspector in New Zealand.
他是这样描述 VARK 来由的
Describing the origins of VARK he says,
我观察到的现象让我困惑  厉害的老师也有教不会的学生
I was puzzled when I observed excellent teachers who did not reach some learners
较差的老师也有能教得会的学生
and poor teachers who did.
我想试试去解决这一问题
I decided to try to solve this puzzle.
当然  我观察到了不少缘由
There are, of course, many reasons for what I observed.
但我觉得有一个原因是最有说服力的
But one topic that seemed to hold some magic, some explanatory power,
那就是「偏好的学习模式」或称「典型偏好」
was preferred modes of learning, modal preferences.
VARK 因此而生
And thus, VARK was born.
原来  没有研究证明学生会天然的分成四个组别
There was no study that revealed students naturally cluster into four distinct groups.
只是有什么魔法  或许能解释
Just some magic that might explain
为什么有些老师能教得会学生  而有些不行
why some teachers can reach students while others can't.
但其原理是什么
But how can this be?
如果我们认可  有些人相对更擅长
If we accept that some people are more skilled at
处理、记忆某几类因素  比如图像或声音
interpreting and remembering certain kinds of stimuli than others like visual or auditory,
为何在学习或者回忆事物的测试中  显示不出差别呢
then why don't we see differences in learning or recall with different presentations?
这是因为  其实人们需要记忆的东西
Well, it's because what we actually want people to recall
并不是图像的精确性质  亦非声音的音调和质量
is not the precise nature of the images or the pitch or quality of the sound.
要记的是各种表现形式背后的「实际含义」
It's the meaning behind the presentations.
有些任务必然需要使用某一类特定的表现形式
There are some tasks that obviously require the use of a particular modality.
比如说  学音乐肯定依赖于声音
Learning about music, for example, should have an auditory component.
类似的  学地理肯定需要看地图
Similarly, learning about geography will involve looking at maps.
有些人天生就比别人更擅长学习某类任务
And some people will have greater aptitude to learn one task over another.
比如说  有绝对音感的人肯定更容易记住音乐中的音调
Someone with perfect pitch, for example,
will be better able to recall certain tones in music.
视觉-空间推理能力强的人  能更准确地在地图上定位国家
Someone with excellent visual-spatial reasoning
will be better at learning the locations of countries on a map.
但学习风格理论宣称  这些偏好性不管学啥东西都是不变的
But the claim of learning style theories is that
these preferences will be consistent across learning domains.
有绝对音感的人  碰到一切声音信息时  都应该学得更快
The person with perfect pitch should learn everything better auditorily
这很明显不合道理
but that is clearly not the case.
大部分人学好地理靠的是地图
Most people will learn geography better with a map.
专家审查了学习风格的文章后  一致认为
Review articles of learning styles consistently conclude
尚没有显著的证据能证明学习风格真的存在
there is no credible evidence that learning styles exist.
在 2009 年的审核中  研究者指出
In a 2009 review, the researchers note,
学习风格论在教育界的流行  跟它缺乏可信证据的事实  形成了鲜明对比
the contrast between the enormous popularity
of the learning styles approach within education
and the lack of credible evidence for its utility is,
我们认为这很离谱  这样的现状让我们很不安
in our opinion, striking and disturbing.
要是对学生的学习风格进行分类有实际作用的话
If classification of students' learning styles has practical utility,
它还需要进一步的证据来证明
it remains to be demonstrated.
我们本来期望的是  在遵循了相符的学习风格的情况下
- What we're expecting is, if your style was honored
你应该比使用了相异学习风格的表现要更好
you're going to perform better than if
you had some experience that conflicted with your style.
我们在这一点上看不到任何支持学习风格论的证据
And this is where we don't see any support for the learning styles theory.
人们对学习风格论如此的深信不疑
- One of the reasons many people find learning styles
或许是因为他们一上来就相信了学习风格的存在
so convincing is because they already believe it to be true.
他们可能已经相信自己是视觉学习者
For example, they might already think that they're a visual learner,
如果老师给他们展示了一份图解  比如说自行车打气筒
and then when a teacher shows them a diagram of, say, a bike pump
然后学生一下子开窍了
and suddenly the concept clicks,
他们就认为  这恰好能作为证据  印证自己是个视觉学习着
well, they interpret this as evidence for their visual learning style.
你先入为主的认为学习方法是正确的
- You already believe that learning styles is right.
当你从实践中获得经验时  你第一时间先想
When you have an experience the first thing you think is,
它符不符合我的学习风格
is that in some way consistent with learning styles?
如果符合  你就不再深入思考了
And if it is, you don't think further.
那说不定是对任何人都有帮助的优质图解
- When in reality that diagram
might just be a great diagram that would have helped anyone learn.
当头脑中已经有了思维定势的框框  认为世界就是这样运行
When we already believe the world to be a certain way,
然后把一切新的经验往框框里套
then we interpret new experiences to fit with those beliefs
而忽略了这经验符不符合「框框」
whether they actually do or not.
那么，如果学习风格对学习并无帮助，那什么才有帮助呢
So if learning styles don't improve learning, then what does?
事实上  有大量文献支持的一个观点是
Well, there's a large body of literature that supports the claim that
使用多种感官形式来学习的效果会优于单一形式
everyone learns better with multimodal approaches
同时展示文本和图像的效果要优于只展现其中一者
where words and pictures are presented together
rather than either words or pictures alone.
接下来  文字是和图像一起展示的
Now there's gonna be words as well as the picture.
看看结果会不会更好一点
We're gonna see if this is any better.
这种效应被称为「多媒体效应」
This is known as the multimedia effect,
它至少在一定程度上解释了
and it explains in part, at least,
拥有图像和旁白的视频  为什么能成为一种强大的学习工具
why videos can be such powerful tools for learning
when the narration complements the visuals.
鸭子
- Duck.
心
- Heart.
在我的博士研究中我发现
- In my PhD research, I found
在物理学入门的多媒体教学中
explicit discussion of misconceptions was essential
对错误概念的明确讨论是至关重要的
in multimedia teaching for introductory physics.
几个了
- How many is that?
六个
- Six.
六个，不错嘛
- Six, okay, that's good.
这好了一半呢
- That is a whole 50% better.
你觉得这样更简单吗
Do you think that was easier?
- 对，百分百更简单
- Yeah, yeah, 100%, 100%.
- 对，有了文字更简单，对
- Yeah, with the words, yeah.
学习中最终极、最重要的特质
- Ultimately, the most important thing for learning
不是呈现信息的方式
is not the way the information is presented
而是学习者脑袋里有何过程
but what is happening inside the learner's head.
人们学得最牢固的时候  是他们活跃地思考材料、
People learn best when they're actively thinking about the material,
解决问题、或是想象不同变量的变化方式
solving problems or imagining what happens if different variables change.
我之前聊过学习的最佳方式、为什么这方式最佳
I talked about how and why we learn best
快去康康我之前的视频「思考的科学」
in my video, "The Science of Thinking" so check that out.
真相是  有许多教学方法已得到证据佐证  有助于学习
Now, the truth is, there are many evidence-based teaching methods that improve learning.
但学习风格论不能算在里面
Learning styles is just not one of them.
鉴于对学习风格广泛存在的误解
And it is likely, given the prevalence of the learning styles misconception
它很可能实际上会让学习效果更差
that it actually makes learning worse.
我的意思是  学习风格论给教师带来了不必要的担心
I mean, learning styles give teachers unnecessary things to worry about,
还导致一些学生不愿参与某些形式的教学
and they make some students reluctant to engage with certain types of instruction.
浪费在学习风格和相关培训上的时间和金钱
And all the time and money spent on learning styles and related training
本可以更好地用于真正改善学习的措施上
could be better spent on interventions that actually improve learning.
你并不是什么视觉、听觉、动手学习者
You are not a visual learner nor an auditory learner nor a kinesthetic learner,
更准确地说  你是依赖于所有感官的学习者  是上面的集合体
or more accurately, you are all these kinds of learner in one.
最好的学习实践  应囊括了对同一事物的多种理解角度
The best learning experiences are those that involve
multiple different ways of understanding the same thing.
并且最好的是  这样的策略不是对一部分人  而是对所有人都适用
And best of all, this strategy works not just for one subset of people but for everyone.